<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="method_xhtml.xsl"?>

<document>

<title lang="en">ASEP/MD Method</title>
<title lang="es">Método ASEP/MD</title>

<paragraph lang="en">
ASEP/MD (averaged solvent electrostatic potential from molecular dynamics) is a QM/MM method that makes use of the mean field approximation (MFA).
As is typical in QM/MM methods, a small part of the full system (which we will call the “solute”, although it need not conform to the usual definition of a solute) is described with quantum-mechanical methods, while the rest of the system (the “solvent”) is described with classical MM force fields.
The basis of the method is to obtain a sampling of the configuration space of a complex system through MD simulations using an MM force field, and to introduce the resulting mean or average environment effect into a QM calculation of the solute.
The method is sequential or asynchronous, not simultaneous, meaning that the QM calculations and the MD simulations are done in separate steps, one after the other, and in an iterative way.
It is also a dual-level method, in the sense that the solute is described as a quantum system during the QM calculations, but through standard classical MM force-field terms during the MD simulations.
On the other hand, the solvent is represented through the same kind of MM terms during the simulations, but it is introduced as a set of external and fixed point charges in the quantum calculations.
</paragraph>

<paragraph lang="en">
A noteworthy feature of the ASEP/MD method is that, since it relies on standard QM and MD methods, it can be applied with any available QM and MD software, with no modification, as long as some minimum requirements are met, such as the possibility of including external charges in QM calculations and of freezing the internal structure of the solute in the MD simulations.
</paragraph>

<paragraph lang="en">
In ASEP/MD, as in general QM/MM methods, the total Hamiltonian is partitioned into three terms:
<equation id="hamiltonian">
<math latex="\hat{H} = \hat{H}_\text{QM} + \hat{H}_\text{MM} + \hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}">H = H_QM + H_MM + H_QM/MM</math> ,
</equation>
where <math latex="\hat{H}_\text{QM}">H_QM</math> is the Hamiltonian corresponding to the quantum subsystem, <math latex="\hat{H}_\text{MM}">H_MM</math> is the energy of the classical subsystem, calculated with classical force-field terms, and <math latex="\hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}">H_QM/MM</math> is the term for the interaction between the two subsystems.
This last term is usually expressed as a sum of two components:
<equation id="hamiltonian-interaction">
<math latex="\hat{H}_\text{QM/MM} = \hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}^\text{elec} + \hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}^\text{vdw}">H_QM/MM = H_QM/MM,elec + H_QM/MM,vdw</math> ,
</equation>
where <math latex="\hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}^\text{elec}">H_QM/MM,elec</math> is the electrostatic interaction and <math latex="\hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}^\text{vdw}">H_QM/MM,vdw</math> includes the van der Waals interaction.
</paragraph>

<paragraph lang="en">
Since the <math latex="\hat{H}_\text{MM}">H_MM</math> term does not involve the quantum subsystem, it can be separated and computed independently.
The remaining terms are included in an effective Schrödinger equation:
<equation id="schroedinger">
<math latex="\left(\hat{H}_\text{QM}+\hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}\right)\left|\Psi\right> = E\left|\Psi\right>">(H_QM + H_QM/MM) |Ψ⟩ = E |Ψ⟩</math> ,
</equation>
where the energy <math>E</math> includes the energy of the quantum subsystem and the interaction energy between the quantum and classical subsystems.
</paragraph>

<paragraph lang="en">
If the solvent is represented by point charges, the electrostatic interaction can be expressed as:
<equation id="electrostatic">
<math latex="\hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}^\text{elec} = \sum_s q_s\hat{V}_s^\text{slt} = \int\hat{\rho}(\vec{r})V^\text{sol}(\vec{r})\;\mathrm{d}\vec{r}">H_QM/MM,elec = sum_s (q_s·V_s,slt) = int (rho(r)·V_sol(r)) dr</math> ,
</equation>
that is, either as a sum over all solvent charges of the charge (<math>q_s</math>) times the electrostatic potential generated by the solute at that point (<math latex="\hat{V}_s^\text{slt}">V_s,slt</math>); or as an integral over the whole space of the solute charge density (<math latex="\hat{\rho}(\vec{r})">rho(r)</math>, including the nuclear charges) times the electrostatic potential generated by the solvent charges (<math latex="V^\text{sol}(\vec{r})">V_sol(r)</math>).
For a given system configuration, the <math latex="\hat{H}_\text{QM/MM}^\text{vdw}">H_QM/MM,vdw</math> term depends only on the nuclear coordinates of solute and solvent, and is therefore a constant that can be taken out of the electronic equation, and the effective Schrödinger equation becomes:
<equation id="schroedinger2">
<math latex="\left(\hat{H}_\text{QM}+\int\hat{\rho}(\vec{r})V^\text{sol}(\vec{r})\;\mathrm{d}\vec{r}\right)\left|\Psi\right> = E\left|\Psi\right>">(H_QM + int (rho(r)·V_sol(r)) dr) |Ψ⟩ = E |Ψ⟩</math> .
</equation>
</paragraph>

<paragraph lang="en">
The ASEP/MD method applies the MFA, and instead of using the solvent electrostatic potential for each configuration (<math latex="V^\text{sol}(\vec{r})">V_sol(r)</math>), which would require performing a large number of quantum calculations, it introduces the average solvent electrostatic potential (ASEP, <math latex="V_m^\text{sol}(\vec{r})">V_m,sol(r)</math>), greatly reducing the number of quantum calculations needed:
<equation id="asep">
<math latex="V_m^\text{sol}(\vec{r}) = \langle V^\text{sol}(\vec{r}) \rangle">V_m,sol(r) = ⟨V_sol(r)⟩</math> ,
</equation>
with which the effective Schrödinger equation reads:
<equation id="schroedinger-asep">
<math latex="\left(\hat{H}_\text{QM}+\int\hat{\rho}(\vec{r})V_m^\text{sol}(\vec{r})\;\mathrm{d}\vec{r}\right)\left|\Psi\right> = E\left|\Psi\right>">(H_QM + int (rho(r)·V_m,sol(r)) dr) |Ψ⟩ = E |Ψ⟩</math> .
</equation>
</paragraph>

<paragraph lang="en">
In practice, it is more convenient to use a discrete analytical representation of the ASEP, instead of the continuous numerical one given by <math latex="V_m^\text{sol}(\vec{r})">V_m,sol(r)</math>.
To get this representation, a set of point charges <math latex="q^\text{ASEP}">q_ASEP</math> is defined, such that they reproduce as closely as possible the ASEP values, at least in the region of space occupied by the solute molecule (where <math latex="\hat{\rho}(\vec{r})">rho(r)</math> is largest):
<equation id="asep-charges">
<math latex="\sum_i \frac{1}{4\pi\epsilon_0}\frac{q_i^\text{ASEP}}{|\vec{r}-\vec{r}_i|} \simeq V_m^\text{sol}(\vec{r})">sum_i ( 1/(4·pi·epsilon_0) q_i,ASEP/|r-r_i| ) ~ V_m,sol(r)</math> ,
</equation>
where <math latex="\vec{r}_i">r_i</math> is the position of the charge <math latex="q_i^\text{ASEP}">q_i,ASEP</math>.
Once the <math latex="q^\text{ASEP}">q_ASEP</math> charges are obtained, they can be directly introduced in the Hamiltonian, as most quantum-chemical software packages allow the specification of a set of external point charges in addition to the nuclei.
</paragraph>

<paragraph lang="en">
The solution of the effective Schrödinger equation yields the wavefunction and properties of the solute, surrounded by the average effect of the solvent.
</paragraph>

</document>
